Why do we meditate?
What do we gain from it?
(Questioner) Snim, thank you
for coming all the way here to us.
I am enrolled
in Buddhism class this fall.
I do 108 prostrations
and meditate every morning.
But, a lot of distracting thoughts arise
when I meditate.
I concentrate, still the thoughts arise,
then I notice to go back to concentration.
Then more thoughts arise.
then 10 minutes pass by quickly.
So, today I sat for 30 more minutes.
But the thoughts still kept arising.
Going on this way,
I don't think I will get to see myself.
So, I am planning to attend
a meditation workshop.
I would like to know why we meditate
and what we gain from it.
And how do we meditate properly?
There is nothing to gain from meditation.
We meditate in order to know
that there is nothing to gain.
That's how I can explain it if I have to.
it is natural to have
all kinds of thoughts arise
when we sit quietly
with our eyes closed.
It's natural
that distracting thoughts arise.
Therefore, putting your attention
on your breath,
in spite of the rising thoughts,
you focus on your breath.
(Questioner) It's not about gaining
anything or finding anything.
But the distracting thoughts
keep coming up.
Of course, they do.
They come up not only for 10
or 30 minutes but for 3000 hours.
If I keep concentrating,
will these thoughts diminish?
Whether you have these thoughts or not
have nothing to do
with the practice of meditation.
Do these thoughts arise
because you want them to
or do they arise naturally?
(Questioner) They arise naturally.
What are you going to do
when they occur naturally?
They will keep arising
until they're done.
If there's more to arise,
they will continue.
This has nothing to do with the Practice.
Just do what you have to do.
Practice doesn't mean
no distracting thoughts.
They have nothing to do with each other.
Our brain structure is such that
when we close our eyes, thoughts arise.
When you close your eyes and sleep,
do you have dreams or not?
You do. It's automatic.
It's as if the live broadcast turns off,
then the recorded broadcast
gets turned on.
With eyes open, the live broadcast runs.
But in sleep with eyes closed,
the recorded tapes go on.
We call them distracting thoughts.
It's normal to have them.
All human brains are wired this way.
If no thoughts arise
when you sit quietly,
then it's a brain made of stone.
Do you also have these
thoughts when you meditate?
(Sunim) Of course I do.
(Audience Laughter)
It's like asking me
if I get hungry when I don't eat.
But if you don't eat for 3 days,
you may feel like dying.
I would get hungry but I would not get
fearful and worry that I would die.
I get hungry, of course, if I don't eat.
I would like to eat.
But we can't eat just because
we want to all the time.
I wouldn't eat because I vowed not
to eat, even though I get hungry.
Likewise, the thoughts arising
when you close your eyes is natural.
Even through those thoughts,
you focus on your breath,
if that is what you have decided to do.
If you decide to focus on your koan,
that's what you do.
If you decide to focus on chanting,
Yes, I understand.
(Applause)
I think you folks do and think
some strange things when you practice.
Find yourself or see yourself?
What is it that you want to see?
It makes sense to say, "see the thoughts"
since they arise in your head.
You can say you see the thoughts.
Can you see them after some practice?
or can you see them naturally?
Can you see them naturally
when you close your eyes?
Or does it take a while
for you to see them?
This room is the same.
When it's dark, we can't see anything.
But, if there are some rays of sun
coming through a hole,
we can see the dust in the light.
Upon seeing the dust, if we sweep them,
do they settle or do we see more of them?
You see more dust.
So, noticing that you have
many distracting thoughts
means that you mind has become clearer.
You are noticing them.
You are having them right now,
but you are not noticing them
because your attention is elsewhere.
You notice them when you are quiet.
They are always there
whether you want them or not.
But usually you are paying
attention to something else.
For example, when you're carrying a child
running to a hospital after an accident,
would you notice your
distracting thoughts or not?
You wouldn't. Why not?
They are there but you don't
notice them because
you are concentrating
on what is going on.
If you focus on your breath,
it's not important whether you
have those thoughts or not.
Because you pay attention to
those thoughts, you can't concentrate.
Lack of concentration on the breath
leads you to blame your thoughts.
Do you folks have more afflictive thoughts
when you're busy or when you're idle?
(Audience) When we are idle.
Right. What is more idle than
sitting with your eyes closed?
Spend a week in a meditation retreat,
you will have more of them.
They will drive you crazy.
They will come up by the droves.
You won't be able to decipher
whether they're dreams or real.
And you asked why we meditate?
If you have a koan,
in the midst of those thoughts,
you concentrate only on the koan.
If focusing on the breath,
there should be no gap
in concentration other than the breath..
It's like driving.
If you keep saying, "He changes his lane."
" He ignores the lights."
"Look at him, he's cutting me off."
You keep saying these things,
you can't drive.
Your anger will crush you.
So, even though there are traffic rules,
in reality, someone will cut you off,
or brake suddenly, etc.
You're a good driver if you can
drive well among those people.
If you drive only when there is
no one around, then even I could drive.
I could drive too if it were
in an open and wide field.
So, in the midst of all kinds of
things arising in the world,
if you are not disturbed by them,
that is true liberation.
When crossing the ocean,
wishing for no wind, no storm,
no big waves is not true freedom.
Let the winds blow,
let the storms come,
Let the big waves rise,
I am not disturbed.
Since I have a great ship
and good sailing skills,
I can handle whatever happens.
This is freedom and is liberation.
Let the distracting thoughts
come as they may.
No need to make them come, no need to
stop them from coming. Just let them be.
No need to make big waves,
no need to pray for no waves.
If there are waves, ride the waves.
If there is no wave,
enjoy the calm. This is life.
This is the goal of our Practice.
Fixing to have no wave is not it.
You go out there and live in the world.
Even living with a kind and loving
person, you are not satisfied completely.
Even your own child whom you
raised doesn't listen to you.
How can you expect the world
to be the way you think it should be?
Prepare with enough clothes
and let the weather cold or hot.
If it gets hot, take a layer off.
If it's cold, put another layer on.
Not being limted by the weather.
This is freedom.
Was Jesus troubled or not
when he was about to be killed?
No, he wasn't. What did he say when he was
about to be nailed on the cross?
"Father, please forgive them."
He wasn't disturbed even by death.
He was on his way,
without much fear of death.
This is different from committing suicide.
So, having distracting thoughts
during meditation is not the problem.
It's normal to have them.
It is not to be disturbed by them.
You are disturbed by those thoughts.
You are quarreling with
the car that cuts you off.
You are asking, " How can I prevent
other cars from barging in?"
This is what you saying.
So, make allowances for those things
but you keep going your way.